# LUCA DI STASIO

# **Postdoctoral Researcher**

Discovery Boulevard, G-3900, KAUST, Thuwal, Saudi Arabia

D-CPR Certified Driving License B (IT)

(+966) 53 419 70 84 luca.distasio@gmail.com

**PROFILE** 

Scientific researcher and software simulation engineer, I'm a creative problem-solver and challenge-driven. Advocate of good coding practices in research to enhance repeatability and openness, I am a founder and active promoter of the Italian Carpentries community.

## **EMPLOYMENT HISTORY**

KAUST Thuwal, Saudi Arabia

Apr 2020 - Present **Postdoctoral Researcher** (with Prof. Brian Moran)

- o Led the development of multiple research projects from idea to publication in the field of large deformation elasticity
- o Developed automated software pipelines for the semi- and un-supervised generation and analysis of models
- o Developed routines for the visualization of multi-dimensional data
- o Disseminated results through the publication of journal articles
- o Presented results at international conferences

UNIVERSITÉ DE LORRAINE Nancy, France

Sep 2020 – Feb 2021 Guest Lecturer

- Established learning objectives, formulated assessment methods and designed learning activities of a Solid Mechanics course for 2<sup>nd</sup> year undergraduate students in Materials Science and Engineering delivered online
- o Delivered learning activities, provided extra-curricular support, and assessed the achievement of learning outcomes
- Managed remotely a team of 5 teaching assistants

#### LULEA UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY

Luleå, Sweden

Jan 2018 – Dec 2019 **Early-stage Researcher** (with Prof. Janis Varna)

- o Completed successfully an international research project between institutions in France, Sweden, and Germany with multiple stakeholders and overlapping requirements
- o Developed automated software pipelines for the semi- and un-supervised generation and analysis of models
- o Co-supervised master students' research projects
- o Disseminated results through the publication of journal articles
- Presented results at international conferences and seminars

# Jan 2018 – Dec 2019 University Teaching Assistant

o Delivered learning activities in the field of Experimental Composite Mechanics to 1<sup>st</sup> and 2<sup>nd</sup> year international master students in Materials Science and Engineering

UNIVERSITÉ DE LORRAINE Nancy, France

## Sep 2016 – Dec 2017 University Teaching Assistant

o Delivered learning activities in the field of Experimental Mechanics, Mechanics of Materials, and Computational Mechanics of Composite Materials to 2<sup>nd</sup> and 3<sup>rd</sup> year undergraduate and 1<sup>st</sup> year graduate students

## Sep 2015 – Dec 2017 Early-stage Researcher (with Prof. Zoubir Ayadi)

- O Kickstarted an international research project (between institutions in France, Sweden and Germany) with multiple stakeholders and overlapping requirements
- O Developed automated software pipelines for the semi- and un-supervised generation and analysis of models
- O Presented results at international conferences and seminars

ETH ZÜRICH Zürich, Switzerland

Sep 2013 – Aug 2015 **Early-stage Researcher** (with Prof. Hans Herrmann)

- o Participated to the development of a coupled LBM-FEM code for staggered fluid-structure interaction
- Optimized the performance of an in-house code for multi-scale modeling of wood

## **IMDEA MATERIALS INSTITUTE**

Madrid, Spain

Nov 2012 – Aug 2013 **Research Assistant** (with Dr. Claudio Lopes)

o Organized and completed successfully an international research project between institutions in Italy and Spain

EDUCATION			
Sep 2015 – Dec 2019	PHD POLYMERIC COMPOSITE MATERIA	ALS	
	Luleå University of Technology	Luleå, Swe	
Sep 2015 – Dec 2019	PHD MATERIALS SCIENCE		
N. 2012	UNIVERSITÉ DE LORRAINE	Nancy, Fra	
Nov 2013	PE INDUSTRIAL ENGINEERING POLITECNICO DI MILANO	Milano, I	
Oct 2010 – Oct 2013	MSC SPACE ENGINEERING	GPA 110/110	
Oct 2010 – Oct 2013	POLITECNICO DI MILANO	Milano, I	
Sep 2011 – Jun 2012	MSC MECHANICAL ENGINEERING	GPA 4/4	
	Drexel University	Philadelphia, U	
Sep 2007 – Sep 2010	BSC AEROSPACE ENGINEERING	GPA 110/110	
	POLITECNICO DI MILANO	Milano, I	
PROFESSIONAL DEV	TELOPMENT (SELECTED)		
Oct – Dec 2021	HIGHER EDUCATION TEACHING CERTIFICATE		
	Harvard University (through HarvardX)	U	
Sep – Nov 2020	CARPENTRIES TRAINER TRAINING		
	THE CARPENTRIES USA		
Jun – Jul 2020	CARPENTRIES MAINTAINER TRAINING		
G 2010 I 2010	THE CARPENTRIES	U	
Sep 2018 – Jan 2019	SWEDISH QUALIFYING COURSE FOR UNIVE LULEA UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY	RSITY TEACHERS Swe	
May Jul 2019	FUNDAMENTALS OF BUSINESS CERTIFICATE		
May – Jul 2018	QUANTIC SCHOOL OF BUSINESS AND TECHNOLOGY (P	PEVIOUSI V	
	SMARTLY)	U	
Mar 2018	RESEARCH FUNDING		
I G 2017	LULEA UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY	Swe	
Jun – Sep 2017	CARPENTRIES INSTRUCTOR TRAINING THE CARPENTRIES	U	
Son Nov 2016		U	
Sep – Nov 2016	PROJECT MANAGEMENT  ECOLE CENTRALE LILLE	Fra	
	Ecoll Cl. Malle Bille	110	
COMPUTER SKILLS	C++ Python Julia Fortran R Matlab	Mathematica Maple	
Windows Batch Unix	•	enFOAM Thermal Desktop	
SQL Git Java	script HTML CSS VBA Excel OpenMP	MPI CUDA OpenACC	
LANGUAGES	Italian Native speaker Eng		
	French Highly proficient Span	nish Highly proficient	

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### PEER-REVIEWED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Di Stasio, L., & Moran, B. (2022). Simplicity on the other side of complexity: asymptotic linearity and superposition at the tip of a Griffith crack in thin neo-Hookean sheets under large deformations. *In preparation*.
- [2] Di Stasio, L., & Moran, B. (2022). Large deformations at the tip of a Barenblatt-Dugdale cohesive crack in thin neo-Hookean sheets. *In preparation*.
- [3] Di Stasio, L., & Moran, B. (2022). Asymptotic and non-asymptotic solutions for cracks in thin neo-Hookean sheets with crack faces loaded by dead and live stress. *In preparation*.
- [4] Di Stasio, L., & Moran, B. (2022). The Cauchy tetrahedron argument in Riemannian geometry and the definition of stress boundary conditions with dead and live loads in finite elasticity. *In preparation*.
- [5] Di Stasio, L., & Moran, B. (2022). Arithmetic progression of sines and cosines and the emergence of symmetry in the elastic behavior of hydrogels. *In preparation*.
- [6] Di Stasio, L., Liu, Y., & Moran, B. (2021). Large deformation near a crack tip in a fiber-reinforced neo-Hookean sheet with discrete and continuous distributions of fiber orientations. *Theoretical and Applied Fracture Mechanics*, 114, 103020. https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tafmec.2021.103020
- [7] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2021). Growth of interface cracks on consecutive fibers: On the same or on the opposite sides? *Materials Today: Proceedings*, 34(1), 360-365. https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.matpr.2020.06.410
- [8] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2020). Effect of the proximity to the 0°/90° interface on Energy Release Rate of fiber/matrix interface crack growth in the 90°-ply of a cross-ply laminate under tensile loading. *Journal of Composite Materials*, 54(21), 3021-3034. https://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0021998320912810
- [9] Di Stasio, L., & Ayadi, Z. (2019). Finite Element solution of the fiber/matrix interface crack problem: Convergence properties and mode mixity of the Virtual Crack Closure Technique. *Finite Elements in Analysis and Design*, *167*, 103332. https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.finel.2019.103]332
- [10] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2019). Energy release rate of the fiber/matrix interface crack in UD composites under transverse loading: Effect of the fiber volume fraction and of the distance to the free surface and to non-adjacent debonds. *Theoretical and Applied Fracture Mechanics*, 103, 102251. https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tafmec.2019.102251

## CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

- [1] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2019). Estimating the average size of fiber/matrix interface cracks in UD and cross-ply laminates. In Turon, A., Maimì, P., & Fagerström, M. (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 7<sup>th</sup> ECCOMAS Thematic Conference on the Mechanical Response of Composites (Composites 2019), Girona, Spain, September 18-20, 2019* (pp. 57-68). Retrieved from https://documentations.wiki/R9NAz/proceeding-composites-2019-v4-pdf.html
- [2] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2018). Effect of boundary conditions on microdamage initiation in thin ply composite laminates. In *Proceedings of the 18<sup>th</sup> European Conference on Composite Materials (ECCM18), Athens, Greece, June 24-28, 2018.* 
  - Retrieved from https://az659834.vo.msecnd.net/eventsairwesteuprod/production-pcoconvin-public/f02831a803b64483b250b93c1536cb00

#### **THESES**

- [1] Di Stasio, L. (2019). *Influence of microstructure on debonding at the fiber/matrix interface in fiber-reinforced polymers under tensile loading* [Doctoral dissertation, Luleå University of Technology and Université de Lorraine]. Digitala Vetenskapliga Arkivet (DiVA). http://urn.kb.se/resolve?urn=urn:nbn:se:ltu:diva-76646 Université de Lorraine thesis repository. http://docnum.univ-lorraine.fr/public/DDOC\_T\_2019\_0229\_DI\_STASIO.pdf
- [2] Di Stasio, L. (2013). Experimental, analytical and numerical investigation of loading rate effects on mode I, mode II and mixed-mode I-II delamination in advanced CFRP [Master's thesis, Politecnico di Milano].

  Digital archive of PhD and post graduate theses (POLITesi). http://hdl.handle.net/10589/82983

## CONFERENCE CONTRIBUTIONS AND SEMINARS

- [1] Di Stasio, L., & Moran, B. (2022, July 7). *A Dugdale-Barenblatt model for cracks in thin neo-Hookean sheets* [Conference session, oral presentation]. 11<sup>th</sup> European Solid Mechanics Conference (ESMC 2022), Galway, Ireland.
- [2] Di Stasio, L. (2020, July 27). *Native scripting in Windows: the Command Prompt interface* [Conference session, oral presentation]. CarpentryCon @ Home 2020 Growing Inclusive, Computational Communities and Leaders, online. https://youtu.be/hRYBGsCxfDY
- [3] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2019, November 6). Towards tough self-healing thin-ply laminates Insights from computational micromechanical modeling and high-temperature experimental investigation of onset and propagation of transverse cracking [Seminar, oral presentation]. LTU Composites Seminars Series, Luleå, Sweden.
- [4] Di Stasio, L., (2019, October 16). Towards tough self-healing thin-ply laminates Insights from computational micromechanical modeling and high-temperature experimental investigation of onset and propagation of transverse cracking [Seminar, oral presentation]. Invited seminar at KTH, Department of Fiber and Polymer Technology, Stockholm, Sweden.
- [5] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2019, September 26). Effect of microstructure on fiber/matrix interface crack growth in UD and cross-ply laminates under tensile loading [Seminar, oral presentation]. Invited seminar at Universidad de Sevilla, ETSI, Elasticity and Strength of Materials Group, Sevilla, Spain.
- [6] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2019, September 18). *Estimating the average size of fiber/matrix interface cracks in UD and cross-ply laminates* [Conference session, oral presentation]. 7<sup>th</sup> ECCOMAS Thematic Conference on the Mechanical Response of Composites (Composites 2019), Girona, Spain.
- [7] Di Stasio, L., (2019, September 17). Ply-thickness and ply-block effect on fiber/matrix interface crack growth in cross-ply laminates under tensile loading [Seminar, oral presentation]. Invited seminar at IMDEA Materials Institute, Madrid, Spain.
- [8] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2019, May 29). *Ply-thickness effect on fiber-matrix interface crack growth* [Conference session, oral presentation]. 9th International Conference on Composite Testing and Model Identification (CompTest2019), Luleå, Sweden.
- [9] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2019, May 8). Growth of interface cracks on consecutive fibers: on the same or on opposite sides? [Conference session, oral presentation]. 12<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Composite Science and Technology (ICCST/12), Sorrento, Italy.
- [10] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2019, April 26). *Investigation of scaling laws of the fiber/matrix interface crack in polymer composites through Finite Element-based micromechanical modeling* [Conference session, oral presentation]. 10<sup>th</sup> EEIGM International Conference on Advanced Materials Research, Moscow, Russia.
- [11] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2018, June 26). *Effect of Boundary Conditions on Microdamage Initiation in Thin Ply Composite Laminates* [Conference session, oral presentation]. 18<sup>th</sup> European Conference on Composite Materials (ECCM18), Athens, Greece.
- [12] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2017, September 12). Finite Elements Solution of the Fiber-Matrix Interface Crack: Effects of Mesh Refinement and Domain Size [Seminar, oral presentation]. DocMASE Summer School 2017, Saarbrücken, Germany.
- [13] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2017, July 5). Micromechanical models of transverse cracking in ultra-thin Fiber-Reinforced Composite laminates [Seminar, oral presentation]. Journée de l'équipe 304 de l'Institut Jean Lamour, Nancy, France.
- [14] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2017, April 6). Micromechanical modeling of thin ply effects on microdamage in Fiber-Reinforced Composite laminates [Conference session, oral presentation]. International Materials Research Meeting in the Greater Region.
- [15] Di Stasio, L., Varna, J., & Ayadi, Z. (2016, May 30). RVE-based Micromechanical Analysis of Fiber-Matrix Debonding in Thin Ply FRPC Laminates [Seminar, oral presentation]. DocMASE Summer School 2016, Luleå, Sweden.
- [16]Di Stasio, L. (2012, July 12). *Modeling complex patterns of crack propagation: branching and merging mechanisms* [Seminar, oral presentation]. Wolfram Summer School 2012, Milton, MA, USA.

**TEACHING** 

**COURSES** 

Sep 2020 - Feb 2021 SOLID MECHANICS (IN FRENCH)

> EEIGM, Université de Lorraine Nancy, France

*Main Instructor(s):* Luca Di Stasio

TA(s): Thomas Villemin, Zoubir Ayadi, Jean-Philippe Tinnes, Marc Ponçot,

Stéphane Andre

2018 - 2019 COMPOSITE MATERIALS

Luleå University of Autum and Spring Term Luleå, Sweden

**TECHNOLOGY** 

Main Instructor(s): Liva Pupure, Janis Varna

TA(s): Luca Di Stasio, Hiba Ben Kahla, Nawres Al-Ramahi

2018 - 2019 AEROSPACE MATERIALS

Spring Term Luleå University of Luleå, Sweden

**TECHNOLOGY** 

Main Instructor(s): Janis Varna

TA(s): Luca Di Stasio, Hiba Ben Kahla, Nawres Al-Ramahi

2018 - 2019 COMPOSITES: DESIGN AND NUMERICAL METHODS

Autum Term Luleå University of Luleå, Sweden

TECHNOLOGY

Main Instructor(s): Andrejs Pupurs

TA(s): Luca Di Stasio

2018 - 2019 MECHANICS OF FIBER COMPOSITES

Luleå University of Luleå, Sweden Spring Term

**TECHNOLOGY** 

*Main Instructor(s):* Liva Pupure

TA(s): Luca Di Stasio

Sep – Dec 2017 COMPOSITE MATERIALS (IN FRENCH)

> EEIGM, Université de Lorraine Nancy, France

*Main Instructor(s):* Yves Meshaka

TA(s): Luca Di Stasio

Sep – Dec 2017 MECHANICS OF MATERIALS I (IN FRENCH)

> EEIGM, UNIVERSITÉ DE LORRAINE Nancy, France

Main Instructor(s): Zoubir Ayadi

Luca Di Stasio, Franck Cleymand, Eloh Komlavi TA(s):

Feb - Jun 2017 SOLID MECHANICS (IN FRENCH)

> EEIGM, UNIVERSITÉ DE LORRAINE Nancy, France

Main Instructor(s): Yves Meshaka Luca Di Stasio TA(s):

LECTURES AND WORKSHOPS

INTRODUCTION TO SCIENTIFIC COMPUTING AND DATA ANALYSIS WITH NUMPY (IN 2022, May 19

ITALIAN)

SOFTWARE SUSTAINABILITY INSTITUTE Online

Main Instructor(s): Luca Di Stasio TA(s): Giacomo Peru

SOFTWARE CARPENTRY WORKSHOP: INTRODUCTION TO PYTHON, SHELL AND GIT (IN

2022, Jan 27-28/Feb 3-4 ITALIAN)

CARPENTRIES ITALIA AND ELIXIR ITALIA Online

Main Instructor(s): Marco Crotti, Silvia Di Giorgio, Luca Di Stasio, Lisanna Paladin, Martino

Sorbaro

Giacomo Peru, Loredana Le Pera TA(s):

2021, Sep 9-10/16-17	SOFTWARE CARPENTRY WORKSHOP: INTRODUCTION TO PYTHON, SHELL AND GIT (I ITALIAN)	
	CARPENTRIES ITALIA	AND ELIXIR ITALIA Online
	Main Instructor(s):	Silvia Bonaiuto, Vincenza Colonna, Marco Crotti, Gianluca Damaggio, Luca Di Stasio, Loredana Le Pera, Mariano Mollo, Giuseppe Profiti, Martino Sorbaro, Allegra Via, Lisanna Paladin
2021, Mar 19/26	SOFTWARE CARPE ITALIAN)	ENTRY WORKSHOP: INTRODUCTION TO PYTHON, SHELL AND GIT (IN
	CARPENTRIES ITALIA	Online
	Main Instructor(s):	Luca Di Stasio, Giorgia Mori, Giacomo Peru, Giuseppe Profiti, Martino Sorbaro
	TA(s):	Fabrizio Donzelli, Annarita Marrano, Mosè Giordano, Loredana Le Pera
2021, Mar 3-4	THE CARPENTRIES	S INSTRUCTOR TRAINING WORKSHOP
·	THE CARPENTRIES	Online
	Main Instructor(s):	Luca Di Stasio, Jason Williams
2020, Oct 21-23	DATA CARPENTRY	GENOMICS WORKSHOP
	NORD UNIVERSITY	Online
	Main Instructor(s): TA(s):	Luca Di Stasio, Endre Sebestyén Abdurhman Kelil Ali, Kari Haugset Alterskjær, Tadeu Fernando Nogueira
2020, Oct 14-16	DATA CARPENTRY NORD UNIVERSITY	Y ECOLOGY WORKSHOP Online
		Luca Di Stasio, Endre Sebestyén Abdurhman Kelil Ali, Kari Haugset Alterskjær, Tadeu Fernando Nogueira
2020, June 22 – July 2	DATA CARPENTRY ECOLOGY WORKSHOP	
	BIOTECH PARTNERS	Online
	Main Instructor(s):	Luca Di Stasio, Rohit Goswami, Sue McClatchy, Chandra Sarkar, Sayane Shome
2020, January 9-10	SOFTWARE CARE PYTHON	PENTRY/LIBRARY CARPENTRY WORKSHOP: INTRODUCTION TO
	KING'S COLLEGE LON	NDON London, UK
	Main Instructor(s): TA(s):	Luca Di Stasio Stefania Marcotti, Walter Muruez Gutierrez, Neil Jakeman, Alessia Visconti, Natasha Romanova, Fiona Wardle
2019, November 21-22	SOFTWARE CARPENTRY WORKSHOP: INTRODUCTION TO PYTHON, SHELL AND G UNIVERSITÄT STUTTGART Stuttgart, G	
	Main Instructor(s): TA(s):	Monah Abou Alezz, Luca Di Stasio Dorothea Iglezakis, Ralf Diestelkämper, Michael Stegmüller, Anett Seeland, Sibylle Hermann
2018, October 9-10	SOFTWARE CARPENTRY WORKSHOP: INTRODUCTION TO R, SHELL AND GIT	
	HPC2N, UMEÅ UNIVERSITY Umeå, Sv	
	Main Instructor(s): TA(s):	Alistair Bailey, Luca Di Stasio Birgitte Briydsö, Pedro Ojeda

ORGANIZATION OF CONFERENCES, SEMINARS AND WORKSHOPS				
2022, Jan 27-28/Feb 3-4	SOFTWARE CARPENTRY WORKSHOP: INTRODUCTION TO PYTHON, SHELL AND GIT (IN ITALIAN)			
2021, Sep 9-10/16-17	SOFTWARE CARPENTRY WORKSHOP: INTRODUCTION TO PYTHON, SHELL AND GIT (IN ITALIAN)			
2021, Mar 19/26	SOFTWARE CARPENTRY WORKSHOP: INTRODUCTION TO PYTHON, SHELL AND GIT (IN ITALIAN)			
2019, May 27-29	9 <sup>TH</sup> International Conference on Composite testing and model identification (CompTest 2019)			

# SCHOLARLY PEER REVIEW

- O JOURNAL OF COMPOSITE MATERIALS
- O JOURNAL OF OPEN RESEARCH SOFTWARE
- O FRATTURA ED INTEGRITÀ STRUTTURALE